Finding Aid for Little Traverse Conservancy Records, 1972-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Little Traverse Conservancy Records 1972-2013 1984-2003
Little Traverse Conservancy.
Harbor Springs, Michigan organization founded in 1972 to promote conservation through land acquisition by donation or purchase, the establishment of nature preserves, and educational programs, rather than through lawsuits or political action. The record group consists of correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, notes, newspaper clippings, press releases, annual reports, and brochures relating to its history and activities. Also included are biographical sketches of founding members based on oral history interviews and some photographs, slides, and architectural drawings. In addition, there are records relating to various outside activities of executive director Tom Bailey.
0082 Bn 2
10.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was received from Thomas C. Bailey of the Little Traverse Conservancy in February 2000. (Donor no. 8937 .) Additional records have been received.
The record group, except for the papers of Thomas Bailey (boxes 5-11) is open for research. The Bailey papers require the written permission of the donor.
The Little Traverse Conservancy, located in Harbor Springs in Michigan's northern Lower Peninsula, is a private, not-for-profit organization dedicated to preserving unique and environmentally sensitive land in northern Michigan through purchase, donation and conservation easement. Its founding members, Dr. John Tanton, David Irish, Frank Pierce, and Earl Larson, along with legal counsel and ally Seberon "Boo" Litzenburger and supporters Ed Koza and John Fischer, originally joined together as the Little Traverse Group in 1972 to file suit to stop two highly commercial developments being planned for the area, Cedar Cove and the Birchwood Farms Project, which they felt were a threat to the area's environment and natural character. Although some modifications to and limits on the developments resulted, the lawsuit was ultimately unsuccessful and it created controversy and resentment within the community.
Because of these problems, the Little Traverse Group decided instead to form a land conservancy, by means of which they would preserve land by buying it rather than fighting expensive, divisive, and potentially unsuccessful legal battles. Thus, the Little Traverse Conservancy was born, incorporating itself in 1972. Models for the new organization were established land conservancies: The Nature Conservancy (a national body) and the Collier County Conservancy in western Florida. In addition, co-founder John Tanton discovered the Summer Resort and Playground Act of 1911, which exempted land held in trust by certain organizations from paying property taxes. This was to prove a great boon to the group.
The early Little Traverse Conservancy (LTC) was led by (and consisted mainly of) its Executive Committee, made up of the original Little Traverse Group members and joinee Wrigley "Bud" Offield. In its initial stage, there was no executive director or any other permanent staff, with day-to-day leadership coming from the Executive Committee and less frequent guidance from the Board of Trustees. All work was done on a volunteer basis. In 1979, the first executive director position was created on a half-time basis, with Kathy Bricker filling the position. The following year, Susanne Dye took over, with C. Louis Borie, LTC's first full-time director, following her. (Further details of this and other key roles within LTC are provided in the organizational chart and timeline at the end of this section.)
With each passing year, LTC grew in membership, staffing, and know-how, as well as increasing the number of its nature preserves and land protection programs. LTC produced its first annual report in 1980. In 1981 it developed the "Friends of the Little Traverse Conservancy" fundraising program, under the strong leadership and tireless efforts of Horace "Huffy" Huffman, an influential leader in numerous areas of the organization for many years.
Huffman was the son of the founder of the bicycle company Huffy Corporation and its CEO before taking early retirement and becoming active in the Little Traverse Conservancy. A Trustee as early as 1972, he served in many different capacities, including vice-president for Membership, in charge of the Friends of the Little Traverse Conservancy Fundraising Program; chairman of the Land Acquisition Program; secretary of the Executive Committee from 1984 to 1987; and chairman of the Building and Grounds Committee. Huffman was responsible for shaping LTC's organizational structure early on and was so personally involved in the fundraising process that he eventually felt the need to train others in this area so that LTC would not become too dependent on any one individual. He also served as a mentor to the executive directors, particularly Tom Bailey.
The first land acquisitions were donated, mainly by group members and their friends and relatives, but in 1984, LTC completed its first land purchase, Orchis Fen. This was also the year that initial work began on the Colonial Point Forest Project, a three-year effort to save a unique parcel of red oak forest that had been recently fallen under the ownership of a lumber company. The organization was progressing internally as well. 1984 saw a move of the LTC office building to its current site at its own Round Lake Nature Preserve; Tom Bailey, longtime and current executive director, came aboard near the end of the year, officially assuming leadership in January of 1985; and Tom Lagerstrom was hired as membership coordinator (later returning as associate director). In 1985, the Colonial Point Forest Project was officially initiated and an endowment fund created to ensure the long-term maintenance of existing and future preserves.
1987 was significant for the foundation of the Business Advisory Committee, which provided a two-way channel of communication between area businesses and the Conservancy and encouraged formal participation by businesses in LTC's conservation efforts. Also in this year, the North Point Preservation Project began. This project's goal was to preserve twenty-eight acres of sand dunes and 2,800 feet of Lake Michigan shoreline in Charlevoix Township. In addition, Huffman retired from his leadership positions in all areas, except for his trusteeship and his chairmanship of the Building and Grounds Committee.
Huffman and his committee undertook a major office and grounds improvement project (his pet project; LTC's office building was later known as "the house that Huffy built") beginning in 1988. The Conservancy launched a new State-Local Government Cooperation program in order to help local units of government with the purchase and planning of land for public parks. It also started a scholarship program, named the Woodbury Ransom Memorial Scholarship in Environmental Studies, at Warren Wilson College in Swannanoa, North Carolina. It was funded through the contribution of an LTC member.
In 1989 LTC started its well-received conservation easement program, which allows landowners to permanently designate parcels of land as natural areas without having to transfer ownership to the Conservancy. Also, Tom Bailey began developing a strategic plan for the Conservancy. The M-119 Scenic Protection Program started in 1990. Its goal was to preserve a border of natural scenery along the roadway. The need for the protection of other areas besides wetlands and forests was also becoming recognized at this time, and LTC started its Farmland Protection Program. In 1991, an addition to the office building (again spearheaded by Huffman) began and was completed over the next year. By 1992, LTC's twentieth anniversary year, staff consisted of seven full-time employees, and over 100 land preservation projects had been completed since the Conservancy's founding.
By 1995 LTC had become such a well-established and professional organization that it was able to serve a crucial role in helping to establish a new land conservancy, the Headlands Conservancy, near Mackinaw City. By this time LTC had become fully professional from within as well, with a comprehensive employee benefits policy and a revised personnel policy firmly in place, both spearheaded by Tom Bailey. In addition, Bailey encouraged staff development, both sponsoring staff training seminars and attending leadership conferences himself. Because of LTC's success, similar organizations began to look to LTC as a model and mentor.
A great blow was dealt to everyone at LTC, professionally and personally, when Horace Huffman died of a heart attack in late November of 1996. The Little Traverse Conservancy carried on, however, and maintains its emphasis on conservation through acquisition of land rather than legal confrontation or political maneuvering.
Among the most significant projects undertaken by the Little Traverse Conservancy were:
Thorne Swift Nature Preserve Project: The Thorne Swift Nature Preserve opened in May of 1983 on thirty acres of land donated by Elizabeth Kennedy. The land is held by LTC and leased to West Traverse Township, which shares management of the preserve with LTC. This is the most 'developed' of LTC's preserves, with board trails over swamps, an interpretive center, two naturalists on staff, and a resident manager. Primary motivations for the preserve were to provide public access to Lake Michigan (much of the lakefront being privately held) and to offer a place for the public to enjoy and learn about nature.
North Point Project: The drive to purchase this land ran from 1987 to 1989 and involved a successful campaign to save twenty-eight acres of sand dunes, along with 2,800 feet of Lake Michigan shoreline, and create a public preserve.
Colonial Point Forest Project: The Colonial Point Forest is a 283-acre stand of red oaks, some as old as 150 years, that was sold to sawmill operator James Devereaux in 1985. Devereaux, realizing the uniqueness of the forest, was actually somewhat reluctant to log it and was willing to sell it to LTC for $1.25 million, provided they could meet the necessary interest payments over a three-year period. LTC launched an extensive fundraising campaign and by 1987 the needed funds were obtained. The forest, once purchased by LTC, was then turned over to the University of Michigan Biological Station, which had been conducting research in the forest for over fifty years prior to its sale. The forest was also opened to the public as a nature preserve.
LTC Organizational Chart and Timeline
Executive Committee Chairperson
1972-1974 Frank Pierce
1975-1976 John Fischer
1977 Maynard Newton
1978-1979 John Tanton
1980-1981 John Fischer
1982-1984 Thomas Pinter
1985-1986 David Irish
1987-1988 John Hall
1989-1990 Marilyn Smith
1991-1992 John Fought
1993-1994 Richard Lent
1995 Joel Moore
1996-1997 Ken Winter
Executive Director
1979 Kathy Bricker
1980-1981 Susanne Dye
1982-1984 Lou Borie
1985-1997 Tom Bailey
Associate Director
1987-1997 Tom Lagerstrom
The records of the Little Traverse Conservancy (LTC) document the organization’s history and dealings. The record group sheds light on the accomplishments of LTC, most notably its land acquisitions, the establishment of its nature preserves, and its environmental education program, as well as its internal organization and growth. In addition, other activities of its members are documented, in particular those of executive director Tom Bailey, who has served in various capacities in several other community- and state-based organizations. The LTC records cover the period from the Conservancy’s founding in 1972 to 2006. The record group is divided into six series: Background Information, Early Board of Trustees Files, the Horace M. Huffman, Jr. Files, Projects, Executive Director Files (Tom Bailey), and Tom Bailey - Other activities. Correspondence in all series is primarily outgoing. Most files are ordered chronologically (generally in reverse chronological order) unless otherwise noted.
Subjects:
Bailey, Tom.; Colonial Point Forest (Mich.); Conservation easements--Michigan, Northern.; Conservation leadership--Michigan, Northern.; Conservation of natural resources--Michigan, Northern.; Conservation projects (Natural resources)--Michigan, Northern.; Conservationists--Michigan, Northern.; Emmet County Park and Recreation Commission.; Emmet County Solid Waste Planning Advisory Committee.; Emmet County (Mich.); Environmental protection--Michigan, Northern.; Fund raising--Michigan, Northern.; Huffman, Horace M.; Isle Royale National Park (Mich.); Landscape protection--Michigan, Northern.; Little Traverse Bay Region (Mich.); Little Traverse Conservancy.; Michigan. Natural Resources Commission.; Natural areas--Interpretive programs--Michigan, Northern.; Natural areas--Michigan, Northern.; Nature centers--Michigan, Northern.; Nature conservation--Michigan, Northern.; North Point Preserve (Mich.); Thorne Swift Nature Preserve (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Colonial Point Forest (Mich.); Conservation & restoration--Michigan--Harbor Springs.; Forest reserves--Michigan.; Forests--Michigan.; Little Traverse Conservancy.; Little Traverse Conservancy--Buildings--Michigan--Harbor Springs.
Contributors:
Bailey, Tom.; Huffman, Horace M.
Genre/Form:
Architectural drawings.; Landscape architecture drawings.; Photographs.
- Background Information
  The Background Information series (3 folders) is made up of two subseries, Articles and publications and Founders' biographies. The Articles and publications subseries is comprised of a file containing clippings and press releases on LTC activities and a folder entitled "Conservation Easements in Northern Michigan: An Information Packet for Landowners." This subseries also contains the LTC quarterly newsletter Update, which contains useful articles on LTC projects, education initiatives, and short biographies of its leaders and prominent members. The Founders' biographies subseries consists of biographical sketches written by John Rohe, an LTC member who is currently working on a biographical book on John Tanton, and Sally Bund, LTC member and archivist at the University of Michigan's Bentley Historical Library.
  - LTC articles and publications, 2 folders
    - LTC published articles: clippings, press releases 1983, annual report, 1979-1984 (Box 1)
    - "Conservation Easements in Northern Michigan: An Information Packet for Landowners," undated (Box 1)
    - UPDATE: quarterly newsletter, 1987-1998
      (missing some issues)
      - 1987-1995 (Box 1)
      - 1996-1998 (Box 1)
  - Founders' Biographies
    - Edward A. Koza August 17, 1999 (Box 1)
    - David Irish September 13, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Seberon Litzenburger November 26, 1999 (Box 1)
    - John H. Tanton, M.D (Box 1)
    - Earl Larson (Box 1)
    - John W. Fischer (Box 1)
- Early Board of Trustees Files
  The first series, Early Board of Trustees Files (1 linear foot), consists of six subseries: Executive director's reports, Administrative documents, Executive Committee and Board of Trustees business, Other committees, LTC budgets, and the John Fischer (early chairman) files. The series as a whole provides a good introduction to the history and early activities of LTC. The first subseries, Executive director's reports, provides useful summaries of the major activities for the years 1980-1983, as do the minutes of the annual meetings from the Executive Committee and Board of Trustees subseries, which cover the years 1972-1985.
  The John Fischer subseries contains some of the earliest items from LTC's history, including the original Articles of Incorporation. It consists of two folders, one arranged chronologically and the other containing miscellaneous undated material. John Fischer, one of the first LTC members, served as chairman in the group's early years, as well as treasurer early on and later. His subseries contains correspondence with founder John Tanton and early LTC documents and writings, including newspaper stories on the group's initial efforts.
  - Executive director's reports
    - Executive director bi-monthly reports September 1980-November 1982 (Box 1)
      (includes reports by executive directors Susanne Dye, Kathy Bricker, and C. Louis Borie)
    - Kathy Bricker activities report: monthly reports to executive director C. Louis Borie by executive assistant 1983 (Box 1)
  - Administrative documents: financial, legal, and insurance-related documents
    - LTC history-archives 1972-1979 (Box 1)
    - Indemnification policy August 1986-May 1987 (Box 1)
    - Land Acquisition policy: reports, policies, articles, correspondence March 1979-February 1987 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee and Board of Trustees business
    - Executive Committee agenda packets, 2 folders
      - 1981-1983 (Box 1)
      - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Ninth annual meeting: agendas, letters of invitation, information packets, minutes 1980 (Box 1)
      (includes correspondence from 1981)
    - Eleventh annual meeting: agendas, letters of invitation, information packets, minutes 1982 (Box 1)
    - Annual meetings: 1-14, minutes 1972-1985 (Box 1)
    - Fall 1992 retreat: agendas, memos, October 14-15, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Maple Leaf Award undated (Box 1)
    - Trustee mailings May 1981-March 1985 (Box 1)
    - Board of Trustees communications July 1984-October 1985 (Box 1)
    - Trustee meeting agenda packets June 1983-December 1985 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee mailings March 1981, January 1982 (Box 1)
    - Next Executive Committee mailing March 1981-July 1982 (Box 1)
  - Other committees
    - Building and Grounds Committee: correspondence, memos, minutes, floor plans, contractors' estimates 1985-1990 (Box 1)
    - Education Committee: correspondence, memos, speeches, minutes, notes 1983-1988 (Box 1)
    - Nominating and Personnel Committee: correspondence, memos, minutes, employment policy drafts 1981-1989 (Box 1)
  - LTC budgets, 3 folders
    (includes annual reports)
    (contents arranged according to divisions within original three-ring binder)
    - 1981-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - Budget correspondence (Box 1)
  - John Fischer files, 3 folders
    (early chairman, include correspondence, mainly with John Tanton; clippings; minutes; speech drafts; group startup information)
    - July 1972-February 1975 (Box 1)
      (no items occurring in March)
    - April 1975-April 1979 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
- Horace M. Huffman, Jr. Files 1972-1994
  The Horace M. Huffman, Jr. Files series (1.7 linear feet) contains the files kept by Huffman who served variously as trustee, vice-president of Membership, Executive Committee secretary and chairman of Building and Grounds Committee. Files relating to the many roles he played in the organization can be found among the contents listing. The extent of Huffman's files indicates the degree of his influence on LTC, given the fact that he was not officially involved with all of the activities that they detail.
  The series consists of topical files arranged alphabetically, with the items within the files in chronological order. These files span the duration of Huffman's tenure at LTC, not just his period as Executive Committee secretary, bearing witness to his strong guiding hand in the affairs of the organization, both in official capacities and from behind the scenes. The Colonial Point-Burt Lake file contains photographs of red oak trees in the Colonial Point Forest and the Office, Powell Road file has photographs of the renovated office exterior.
  Other significant items in the series include correspondence relating to the Tip of the Mitt Watershed Council, of which Huffman was a founder and strong supporting member, and which shared office space with the Little Traverse Conservancy. Part of its role is ensuring clean waterways in the region, and its stance is one of more open advocacy than is LTC's. The Inland Lakes Program file was compiled by Huffman as part of the Watershed Council rather than LTC and contains a letter with a brief description of how the two organizations differ.
  It should be noted that the files entitled "Cement Plant, Petoskey," "Dundee Cement Plant," and "Holnam Project" all refer to the same endeavor: the attempt by LTC to secure the site of a former cement plant in Petoskey (owned by the Holnam Company, which has another, active plant in Dundee, in southeastern lower Michigan) for preservation. During this same time, a developer by the name of LoPatin was in competing negotiations with Holnam to purchase the site in order to turn it into a resort area.
  - Activity reports 1986-1989 (Box 2)
  - Annual meeting 1986-1989 (Box 2)
  - Annual reports, 2 folders
    - 1981-1985, 1987 (Box 2)
    - 1988-1994 (Box 2)
  - L'Arbre Croche 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - L'Arbre Croche mailings 1981-1984 (Box 2)
  - Bear River Project February 1983 (Box 2)
  - Birchwood 1983 (Box 2)
  - Board nominees 1984 (Box 2)
  - Board of Trustees and Executive Committee minutes 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Breakers East 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Budgets 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Building and Grounds 1985-1993, 2 folders (Box 2)
    (includes before and after photographs and negatives of the renovated LTC office)
  - Business Council 1986 (Box 2)
  - Bylaws 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Cedar Cove December 1984 (Box 2)
  - Cement Plant, Petoskey 1982-1994 (Box 2)
  - Charlevoix 1984-1986 (Box 2)
  - Colonial Point 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Colonial Point, general 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Colonial Point reports April-May 1986 (Box 2)
  - Colonial Point-Burt Lake 1981-1987 (Box 2)
    (includes photographs and slides of the Colonial Point Forest)
  - Community Foundation: Petoskey, Emmet undated (Box 2)
  - Computer grants 1983 (Box 2)
  - Cudlip property 1986 (Box 2)
  - Dundee Cement Plant July 1990 (Box 2)
  - Emergency fund June 1985 (Box 2)
  - Endowment 1993 (Box 2)
  - Endowment program 1988 (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee agendas and minutes 1981-1983 (Box 2)
  - Financial reports, quarterly 1981-1987 (Box 2)
  - Frey, Ed J. 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Frey Foundation January-March 1991 (Box 2)
  - Gateway to Harbor 1972-1978 (Box 2)
  - Growth and Development Forum August 1990 (Box 2)
  - H.M.H., Board and resignation 1987 (Box 2)
    (Horace M. Huffman)
  - Harbor Plan June-July 1982 (Box 2)
  - Historical papers 1973-1979 (Box 2)
  - Holnam project 1991-1993 (Box 2)
  - Inland Lakes Program 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Job descriptions undated (Box 2)
  - Kresge Foundation 1984-1986 (Box 2)
  - Kruzel Bog 1983 (Box 2)
    (also known as Orchis Fen)
  - LTC Business Council 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - LTC name change 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Lagerstrom employment agreement October-November 1986 (Box 2)
  - Lake Shore Association 1980-1984 (Box 2)
  - Lakeside letters 1983 (Box 2)
  - Land acquisitions, future June 1986 (Box 2)
  - Leelanau Conservancy 1990-1995 (Box 2)
  - Long range planning 1988-1991 (Box 2)
  - McKellar, Doug: correspondence February-April 1985 (Box 3)
  - Membership goals 1987 (Box 3)
  - Membership secretary 1983-1986 (Box 3)
  - Menonaqua: Pailthorpe land, L'Arbre Croche purchase June-July 1984 (Box 3)
  - Menonaqua trails 1984-1988 (Box 3)
  - Nature Conservancy, TNC 1981-1983 (Box 3)
  - Nature preserves October 1984 (Box 3)
  - Office, Powell Road 1982-1991 (Box 3)
    (includes photographs of completed renovations to the LTC office)
  - Offield, Bud 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Organizational chart and job descriptions 1981-1987 (Box 3)
  - Otis Lane land conservation agreement August 1992 (Box 3)
  - Personnel: Nominating Committee 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Planned Giving 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Pointner correspondence 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - Policy Committee memos 1993 (Box 3)
  - Policy manual December 1985 (Box 3)
  - Pooled Income Trust Fund 1983-1989 (Box 3)